A Guide to the Henkel family records, 1838-1903
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Henkel family records, 1838-1903
The Library of Virginia
28040
15 cu. ft. (137 volumes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased 19 April and 17 July 1973.
Biographical Information
The Henkel family of New Market, Shenandoah County, Virginia, was a prominent family of Evangelical Lutheran ministers and printers. Paul Henkel (1754-1825) moved with his family to New Market in 1790, and the next year established St. Davidsburg Church. He also established churches in Augusta County, Virginia, and was one of the founders of the Lutheran Synod of North Carolina. His missionary journeys took him into Ohio, Indiana, Kentucky, and Tennessee. He left a large number of descendants, many of whom were ministers, physicians, printers, and merchants. He married Elizabeth (Negeley) Henkel (1757-1843) on 20 November 1776 and they had nine children. Many of the family members were buried in the Emmanuel Lutheran Church Cemetery near New Market, Virginia.
Solomon Henkel (1777-1847), son of Paul and Elizabeth Henkel, practiced medicine in New Market. He also served as postmaster and operated a printing press with his brother Ambrose (1786-1870), who was also a writer and Lutheran minister. Solomon married Rebecca Miller (1780-1854) on 9 September 1800. Their children included: Helena (1801-1823), Seorim (1803-1804), Sylvanus (1805-1830), Samuel Godfrey (1807-1863), Siram Peter (1809-1879), Simeon Socrates (1811-1812), Silon Amos (1813-1844), Solomon David (1815-1872), and Solon Paul Charles (1818-1882).
At various times the Henkel brothers were involved in the dry goods store in New Market and the mill at Plains Mills in Rockingham County. The store was known at different times as Silon A. Henkel and Company; Solomon D. Henkel and Brothers; J. H. Tinsinger and Henkel; Henkel, Koiner, and Company; D. S. Henkel and Brothers; and L. P. Henkel and Brothers.
Samuel Godfrey Henkel was a physician and married to Susan Koiner (1810-1905). Silon Amos Henkel was a physician and married Elizabeth Shaffer (1822-1894) on 18 August 1842. Solomon David Henkel (1815-1872) married Sarah Bowman (1816-1902) on 11 June 1840, daughter of John and Catherine Minnick Bowman. Solon Paul Charles Henkel was a physician and married Anna Maria Miller (1827-1911) on 25 November 1847. Both Silon Amos and Solon Paul Charles attended the University of Pennsylvania medical department.
Siram Peter Henkel (1809-1879) married Margaret Koiner (1820-1899) on 30 June 1835. They had thirteen children including Louis Philip (1837-1904) and Julia Annette (1859-1911). Louis Philip married 5 April 1872 to Anna Maria Moore (1837-1919) and was a merchant in New Market (L. P. Henkel and Brothers). Many members of the family resided at Plains Mills. Julia Annette Henkel married 26 December 1883 to Joseph Homer Tinsinger (1853-1938). In the 1890s Joseph operated a general store with members of the Henkel family.
Noah Isiah Henkel (1814-1885) was the son of Ambrose Henkel(1786-1870) and was a merchant in New Market. He married 8 November 1836 to Mary Magdalena Zirkle (1816-1896).
Scope and Content
Business records, 1838-1903, of the Henkel family of New Market, Virginia, including accounts, cash books, daybooks, inventories, ledgers, and minute books. The records document the many business and agricultural interests of the family including a general store in New Market, farms, New Market River Bridge Company, mill in Plains Mills, and scales owned by several family members.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: General Store [New Market, Va.], 1838-1903
Series II: Plains Mills [Rockingham County, Va.], 1856-1894
Series III: Miscellaneous, 1868-1903
Contents List
- Series I: General Store [New Market, Va.], 1838-1903., Extent: 39 boxes (9.75 cu. ft.). (Box 1-39)
  Records, 1838-1903, of a general store in New Market, owned by several members of the Henkel family. All of the ledgers were not identified so it is unknown if these records belonged to one or several stores. Ledgers were identified at different times as Silon A. Henkel and Company; Solomon D. Henkel and Brothers; J. H. Tinsinger and Henkel; Henkel, Koiner, and Company; D. S. Henkel and Brothers; and L. P. Henkel and Brothers. Most of the volumes relate to L. P. Henkel and Brothers.
  Included are account books, cash books, day books, and ledgers. Information found includes name of customer, items purchased, quantity of items purchased, form of payment, amount owed, and amount paid. Items sold include dry goods, molassas, clothing, tobacco, spikes, shoes, meats, liquor, bacon, oil, and other sundry items. Forms of payments include cash, credit, labor, and barter of items such as butter, eggs, and chicken.
  Alphabetically by title.
  - Account book, 1850-1855. (Box 1)
    Accounts with wholesalers.
  - Account book, 1860-1871. (Box 1)
    Includes New Market hay and cattle scale account book and accounts with merchants for purchases of shoes, coal, tobacco, flour, and other dry goods. Also includes dates of the arrival Union troops in New Market, list of flour furnished to soldier families, sale of flour to Shenandoah County clerk, and flour mills, 1864-1865.
  - Account book, 1869-1872. (Box 1)
    L. P. Henkel and Brothers accounts with wholesalers. The receipts were pasted in a volume on top of a Register of Conscripts from the 10th Congressional District and Special Orders, 1863-1864. The Register of Conscripts was microfilmed and is available on Misc. reel 5495, LVA Acc. 43957.
  - Account book, 1870-1873. (Box 2)
    Accounts with wholesalers. Indexed.
  - Account book, 1872-1874. (Box 2)
    L. P. Henkel and Brothers account with wholesalers. Includes an inventory of stock of goods, 1872-1873. Indexed.
  - Account book, 1874-1876. (Box 2)
    L. P. Henkel and Brothers account with New Market bank.
  - Account book, 1889-1894. (Box 2)
  - Account book, 1891-1899. (Box 2)
    L. P. Henkel and Brothers accounts with wholesalers.
  - Account book, nd. (Box 2)
  - Bank book, 1885-1887. (Box 3)
    Silon A. Henkel and Company.
  - Bank book, 1889-1891. (Box 3)
    L. P. Henkel and Company.
  - Cash book, 1885-1886. (Box 3)
    S. A. Henkel and Company.
  - Cash book, 1887-1889. (Box 3)
  - Cash book, 1889-1891. (Box 3)
  - Day book, 1856-1858. (Box 4)
  - Day book, 1861-1862. (Box 5)
    Solomon D. Henkel and Brothers.
  - Day book, 1862-1865. (Box 5)
  - Day book, 1865-1866. (Box 5)
  - Day book, 1865-1867. (Box 6)
    Solomon D. Henkel.
  - Day book, 1866-1867. (Box 6)
    L. P. Henkel.
  - Day book, 1867 August-1868 July. (Box 7)
  - Day book, 1867 December-1868 November. (Box 7)
  - Day book, 1868 July-1869 January. (Box 8)
  - Day book, 1868 November-1869 November. (Box 8)
  - Day book, 1869 January-August 1870. (Box 9)
  - Day book, 1869 November-1870 November. (Box 9)
  - Day book, 1870-1871. (Box 10)
  - Day book, 1871-1872. (Box 10)
    Solomon D. Henkel and Silon A. Henkel.
  - Day book, 1872. (Box 10)
  - Day book, 1872-1873. (Box 11)
    L. P. Henkel and Brothers.
  - Day book, 1873-1874. (Box 11)
    L. P. Henkel and Brothers Day Book B.
  - Day book, 1874 June-October. (Box 12)
  - Day book, 1874 June-December. (Box 12)
  - Day book, 1874 December-1875 March. (Box 12)
  - Day book, 1874-1878. (Box 12)
  - Day book, 1875-1876. (Box 13)
    Frank L. Henkel, Cowan's Station.
  - Day book, 1876-1877. (Box 13)
  - Day book, 1877-1878. (Box 14)
  - Day book, 1879-1881. (Box 14)
  - Day book, 1881-1883. (Box 14)
  - Day book, 1884. (Box 15)
  - Day book, 1885. (Box 15)
  - Day book, 1886 March-May. (Box 16)
  - Day book, 1886 May-July. (Box 16)
  - Day book, 1886 July-September. (Box 16)
  - Day book, 1886 July-1887 January. (Box 16)
  - Day book, 1886 September-October. (Box 16)
  - Day book, 1886 September-October. (Box 16)
  - Day book, 1886 October-November. (Box 16)
  - Day book, 1886 November-December. (Box 16)
  - Day book, 1886 November-December. (Box 16)
  - Day book, 1887 January-May. (Box 16)
  - Day book, 1887 January-May. (Box 16)
  - Day book, 1887 May-August. (Box 16)
  - Day book, 1887 August-December. (Box 17)
  - Day book, 1887 August-1888 January. (Box 17)
  - Day book, 1887 December-1888 July. (Box 17)
  - Day book, 1888. (Box 18)
  - Day book, 1888. (Box 18)
  - Day book, 1888 July-1889 January. (Box 18)
  - Day book, 1889 January-June. (Box 19)
  - Day book, 1889 June 26-November 16. (Box 19)
  - Day book, 1889 June 27-November 14. (Box 19)
  - Day book, 1890 January 25-July 4. (Box 19)
  - Day book, 1890 January 27-June 25. (Box 19)
  - Day book, 1890 July 4-November 5. (Box 20)
  - Day book, 1890 July 7-November 7. (Box 20)
  - Day book, 1890 November 8-1891 March 6. (Box 20)
  - Day book, 1890 November 8-1891 March 6. (Box 20)
  - Day book, 1891 March-April. (Box 21)
  - Day book, 1891 April 12-June 15. (Box 21)
  - Day book, 1891 April 20-June 10. (Box 21)
  - Day book, 1891 June 6-December 1. (Box 21)
  - Day book, 1891 June 13-December 19. (Box 21)
  - Day book, 1891 December 2-1892 April 18. (Box 22)
  - Day book, 1891 December 19-1892 April 21. (Box 22)
  - Day book, 1892 April 21-17 September. (Box 22)
  - Day book, 1892 April 22-14 September. (Box 23)
  - Day book, 1892 September 19-27 February 1893. (Box 23)
  - Day book, 1892 September 19-28 February 1893. (Box 24)
  - Day book, 1893 March 1- July 7. (Box 24)
  - Day book, 1893 March 11-28 June. (Box 24)
  - Day book, 1893 July 8-1 December. (Box 25)
  - Day book, 1893 July 8-6 December. (Box 25)
  - Day book, 1893 December 7-1894 May 24. (Box 25)
  - Day book, 1893 December 7-1894 May 25. (Box 26)
  - Day book, 1894 May 25- 1895 January 30. (Box 26)
  - Day book, 1895 January 31-25 December. (Box 27)
  - Day book, 1895 January 31-1896 January 30. (Box 27)
  - Day book, 1896 July 29-1897 May 17. (Box 27)
  - Day book, 1897 May 17-November 17. (Box 28)
  - Day book, 1897 November 18-1902 August. (Box 28)
  - Financial statement, 1850-1881. (Box 28)
    A Schedule of the Notes, Accounts, and a Settlement of the Partnership Transactions of Solomon D. Henkel and Brothers. Partnership is between Samuel G., Solomon D., Solon P.C., and Siram P. Henkel.
  - Inventory, cash book, and special accounts, 1875-1879. (Box 28)
  - Inventories and wheat and fertilizer accounts, 1879-1880, 1896-1897. (Box 29)
  - Inventory book, 1887-1888. (Box 29)
  - Inventory and cash book, 1885, 1889. (Box 29)
    Inventory of goods of S. A. Henkel and Company to L. P. Henkel and Company.
  - Journal, 1884-1891. (Box 29)
    Wagon Book B - Henkel, Graves, and Company.
  - Ledger, 1838-1851. (Box 30)
  - Ledger, 1854-1866. (Box 31)
    Indexed.
  - Ledger, 1865-1867. (Box 32)
  - Ledger, 1867-1870. (Box 32)
  - Ledger, 1867-1872. (Box 33)
    Indexed. Solomon P. Henkel Ledger B.
  - Ledger, 1871-1880. (Box 34)
    Indexed. Includes Statement of Phosphates sold, 1879 (pp. 310-312).
  - Ledger, 1873-1874. (Box 35)
  - Ledger, 1875-1876. (Box 36)
    Henkel Koiner and Company.
  - Ledger, 1875-1879. (Box 36)
    Indexed. Franklin L. Henkel and Company.
  - Ledger, 1877-1879. (Box 36)
    Indexed. Wagon book B and Day book.
  - Ledger, 1877-1880. (Box 37)
    Indexed. D. S. Henkel and Brothers.
  - Ledger, 1885-1887. (Box 37)
    Indexed. L. P. Henkel and Company Ledger A.
  - Ledger, 1885-1889. (Box 37)
    Indexed. S. A. Henkel.
  - Ledger, 1888-1894. (Box 38)
    Indexed. L. P. Henkel and Company.
  - Ledger, 1894-1903. (Box 39)
- Series II: Plains Mills [Rockingham County, Va.], 1856-1897., Extent: 4 boxes and 1 volume on shelf (1.1 cu. ft.). (Box 40-43)
  Records, 1856-1897, of Plains Mills, 1856-1894, a flour milling business located in Rockingham County, Virginia. Included are account books, day books, and ledgers. Entered in the volumes are charges for the milling of corn and wheat and sawing of lumber. The records also contains profit and loss statements, and wheat, flour, expense and cash accounts. Of note are entries in the account and day books containing names of workers, work performed, amount of time, and pay. Many members of the family of Siram Peter and Margaret Koiner Henkel resided at Plains Mills.
  - Account book, 1869-1874. (Box 40)
  - Account book, 1881-1883. (Box 40)
  - Account book, 1883-1884. (Box 40)
    Workers account book includes name of workers, work performed and amount of time, and pay. Work included thinning corn, making hay, and shucking corn. Workers were paid in money and food. Some workers boarded and included are notes on number of meals taken and cost per meal.
  - Account book, 1889-1891. (Box 40)
    Brickyard accounts, lumber for Emmanuel Lutheran Church, and stud book for horse Shannon.
  - Day book, 1856-1860. (Box 40)
    Day book of Siram P. Henkel, No. 1, Plains Mills Farm, Rockingham County, Virginia.
  - Day book, 1860-1868. (Box 41)
    Day book of Siram P. Henkel, No. 3, Plains Mills Farm, Rockingham County, Virginia. Includes entries for the Confederate States.
  - Day book, 1874-1878. (Box 41)
    Day book of Siram P. Henkel, No. 5, Plains Mills Farm, Rockingham County, Virginia.
  - Day book, 1874-1878. (Box 41)
    Milling daybook.
  - Day book, 1884-1887. (Box 41)
    Includes inventory, 1897.
  - Day book, 1887-1891. (Box 42)
  - Day book, 1889-1891. (Box 42)
  - Day book, 1892-1893. (Box 42)
  - Day book, 1893-1894. (Box 42)
  - Ledger, 1869-1877. (Box 43)
  - Ledger, 1869-1880. (Box 43)
    Henkel and Brothers.
  - Ledger, 1888-1897. (Volume on shelf)
- Series III: Miscellaneous, 1868-1903., Extent: 2 boxes (.5 cu. ft.). (Box 44-45)
  Records, 1868-1903, including account books, ledgers, and minutes for various companies that were partly owned by members of the Henkel family or family members served on the boards. Includes a ledger for a grocery run by Henkel and Joseph Tinsinger, in-law; saw mill accounts; scale ledgers; and a minute book of the New Market River Bridge Company.
  Of note is the minute book, 1868-1887, of the New River Bridge Company. The Company was incorporated in 1869 by W. M. Sibert, D. F. Kazey, A. S. Miller, Thomas Moore, J. B. Strayer, B. Z. Price, C. C. Henkel, and L. M. Henkel. The company was formed to construct a turnpike from New Market to New Market station on the Orange, Alexandria, and Manassas railroad, and to erect a bridge over the North Shenandoah River. In 1877 S. P. C. Henkel, Thomas Moore, Christian Shirley, D. F. Kazey, W. H. Rice, S.P. Shirley, and L. P. Henkel assumed partnership of the company.
  - Hay, millwork, and apple accounts, 1893-1895. (Box 44)
  - Saw mill accounts, 1890. (Box 44)
  - Scale book, 1887-1888. (Box 44)
  - Scale book, 1888-1890. (Box 44)
  - Scale book, 1898-1903. (Box 44)
    J. H. Rupp, weighmaster.
  - Tinsinger and Henkel ledger, 1889-1891. (Box 45)
    Indexed. Located in Mt. Jackson, Virginia. Was J. H. Tinsinger and later Tinsinger and Henkel. Dealers in Fresh meats, sausage, lard, bacon, flour, also family groceries.
  - New Market River Bridge Company, 1868-1877, 1886-1887. (Box 45)
    Minute, ledger, and cash book.